Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna's Part Three.
We've reached Chapter 15,
titled "An Investigation into the Nature of Things."
In Tibetan, here we see
it called RANG BZHIN BRTAG PA
RANG BZHIN BRTAG PA
BRTAG PA, meaning PARIKSHA, which means...
- [Female voice] Research
- A study.
RANG BZHIN is an interesting word
because it means "its own surface."
BZHIN here means surface.
BZHIN RAS refers to surface.
So RANG BZHIN refers to the
"surface" of something. It
means nature, meaning... Let's make it
clear from the beginning, shall we?
He is referring to the characteristics of things: their inherent nature,
a certain quality inherent in things.
So you have to have this feeling...
We are going to explore, for example,
whether fire has a characteristic or inherent nature that it
can generate heat, and then this nature will be activated
and expressed in the world.
Is the inherent nature of fire heat?
Then, for some reason, it went viral and spread
.
Does it have its own unique characteristics?
So when we talk about nature
or self-nature (svabhava) here,
RANG BZHIN, think about it,
this is a thing deep within things,
this is its true nature,
think about its nature.
Okay, now let's look at our argument.
First passage,
verse 1.5:
,RANG BZHIN RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS NI, ,
'BYUNG BAR RIGS PA MA YIN NO,
,RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS BYUNG BA YI,
,RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN DU 'GYUR,
If you think carefully,
if the characteristics of something are part of it,
it doesn't need to be created.
If the characteristics of an object are inherent in itself—
that is, the meaning of characteristics—
they should not be something
you only receive when something else happens.
It must be something you're born with. It's something you're born with
.
There is no need to heat the fire
[rubbing hands]. Fire is
inherently hot.
So if something must be done first to make the
fire hot, then heat is not the nature of fire. Do you
agree? - agree. If
other things need to be done,
if another fire must be lit below the fire to
make it hot,
then the nature of fire—
we would not say that heat is the nature of fire.
Therefore, we can say that nature or characteristics
come from the things themselves,
rather than being qualities that only appear when other things exist or when
other causes or conditions exist
.
,RANG BZHIN RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS NI,
,'BYUNG BAR RIGS PA MA YIN NO,
This is inappropriate.
If the existence of the inherent characteristics of something
requires the occurrence of other things, there
must be some cause or condition.
,RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS GANGS BYUNG BA YI,
,RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN DU 'GYUR,
Because the nature of what is caused by other factors or causes
is artificial, and the
meaning of artificial is the opposite of that of nature.
They were put together and then thrown into the fire.
Oh, come here, let me heat it up for you.
[Rubbing hands together]
Then the fire gets hot.
Then the nature of fire would not
exist in fire itself.
It will be artificially created
and then given to fire.
Okay, do you understand?
RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN
Therefore, BYAS PA CAN here refers to something that is
almost man-made or created.
In the jewelry industry, there are real
rubies and sapphires,
as well as fakes.
But when people learned to
create real
rubies and sapphires in the laboratory,
there was a great debate about
whether they should be called artificial stones.
Those who succeeded in the process argued that
it was not man-made, but real.
Another person argued that if it wasn't
dug out of the soil and rocks, then it was
n't real.
So they reached a compromise, which they
called "making rubies". It
sounds better than artificial products or substitutes.
So this was created,
not natural.
This is the key point.
RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN ZHES BYAR
If the nature or characteristics of something
must be created from the outside,
JI LTAR BUR NA RUNG BAR 'GYUR
Then how can it be said to be nature?
It is man-made, created. Do you
understand?
It's like making a ruby.
good.
Nagarjuna Bodhisattva...
This is a story.
There's a story behind this photo.
My Lama, as I have told you,
I served as a volunteer for my teacher for
30 years, and for about 25 of those years
I was his driver,
traveling him between New Jersey and Washington, D.C.
That's a five-hour drive.
He used to teach there once a month.
So I've done it over 300 times.
I told him to go there.
If we count the round trips, there are a total of 600 trips.
So I know those routes by heart,
and I really enjoy driving him.
Because he always refuses to answer my questions.
He couldn't refuse in the car.
He was locked in the car for five hours,
and the car he ordered didn't have a radio,
so I couldn't listen to the radio.
Ordering a car without a radio
requires an extra fee.
[Laughter]
In short, all we can do is discuss Buddhism.
Sometimes he would pretend to be asleep.
I would say I know you're not asleep.
Then he...
[imitates snoring]
Anyway, he always
stops at Howard Johnson's restaurant in front of the Delaware Bridge, which is located at the intersection of Maryland and Delaware.
We always stopped at the same spot, and he
would order tea. As
you know, he loves drinking tea.
He drinks about 15 cups of tea a day
. I make him 15-20 cups of tea a day.
They will try to provide him with creamer.
He would say, "No,
I want cream." "That's creamer, I don't want creamer.
I want cream, I want the real thing."
He taught me these words:
artificial, fake, unnatural.
Everything I learned from him,
including my own use of words, has a
structure.
We were sitting somewhere, and he said,
"This is called BCOS MA."
BCOS MA stands for BYAS PA.
BYAS PA means that it must be
created from the outside world.
This is not natural.
good.
He hates this stuff, he
really does.
good.
Next paragraph. It is actually only half a section.
This is actually RANG LUGS.
What does that mean?
This is our argument.
,RANG BZHIN DAG NI BCOS MIN DANG,
,GZHAN LA LTOS PA MED PA YIN,
If it is a real characteristic, it
should not be BCOS MA.
BCOS MA means man-made or
artificial creation. It
shouldn't taste like creamer. It must
be true.
BCOS MIN means non-creative.
What is the famous BCOS PA in the Stages of the Path?
BCOS MA? It means trying to feel like a Bodhisattva
when you are not yet one
.
[Laughter]
That's good, BCOS MA.
Good. A fake Bodhisattva. The
Bodhisattva created.
Artificial, you pretend to be a bodhisattva,
but then you still mess around all day, and things like that.
,GZHAN LA LTOS PA MED PA YIN,
If it is the true nature, it
should not need to rely on any
external conditions to exist.
If fire is inherently hot, then it doesn't matter
where the fire is or
what happens to it.
He should be warm from the inside out.
Like this.
This is our definition of nature.
I was thinking, maybe you
could consider it. Is
this BTAGS PA MTHA'
BZUNG GI RIGS PA? Is
BZUNG GI RIGS PA?
This is a very, very useful expression.
I remember once I was debating Buddhist scriptures
at Drepung Monastery.
I heard this statement, BTAGS
PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS PA.
BTAGS PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS
PA, means theoretical argument.
Theoretical case studies.
In theoretical cases, the nature of things
should possess two qualities. What is it?
BCOS MIN
should not be a human creation; it
should be GZHAN LA LTOS PA MED PA.
It should not
depend on other conditions.
So, does such an inherent property exist?
This is another debate, you know?
Theoretically speaking, we said
theoretically, right? Theoretically
speaking, that's just how it is. Do
you know if
such a thing actually exists? We don't know.
Lama Qiuni also expressed his views.
This is a very traditional and ancient view
about what nature should be like if it truly exists
, and that it
should possess three qualities.
Ready?
First.
GNYUG MA'I NGO BO
GNYUG MA is a very, very rare and
important word, meaning since beginningless time
[laughter].
GNYUG MA
sounds like SMYUG MA,
which means "bamboo shoot," but it doesn't.
GNYUG MA means original,
primitive, from the very beginning.
GNYUG MAGNYUG MA'I NGO BO
If this is the nature of fire,
then this nature will always exist within fire. Do you
understand?
It refers to heat, intense heat.
If...
if fire has an inherent nature, then
that nature or characteristic
will always exist within those things
as long as fire exists.
That's the first point.
Fire is always hot.
Second point.
Whether you're discussing fire a hundred years ago,
fire a hundred years from now,
or the fire in this room right now,
it should remain unchanged.
Features will always exist.
Whether you're talking about fire a hundred years from now,
fire a hundred years ago,
or fire right now, the
characteristics of fire remain.
hot.
Third point.
Its properties should not depend on
other sources.
He also gave an interesting example.
You don't need to put a kettle on the stove.
Veronica and I recently
got something really cool that
someone gave us. Was it a
cherry pit? It
was in a bag?
It also contains lavender flowers.
Put it in the microwave to heat it up,
and then lie on it. It's
very comfortable to sleep like this. It will
stay warm for about half an hour, then
gradually cool down, and you can lie down on it and fall asleep. It
is very comfortable.
It looks a bit like a kettle.
In short, Lama Qiuni said that
if the heat of the fire comes from within, there is
no need to
heat the fire with a kettle.
This is a pillow filled with cherry pits and
lavender.
If you don't need to microwave a cherry pit lavender pillow
to warm yourself up,
you're probably warmed by nature. Do you
understand?
These are the three key elements. Once
again, this might be BTAGS
PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS PA.
In the photo, a woman is about to touch the candlelight.
You might say something like, "
I hope she doesn't put her fingers in the fire
because it will burn her."
You might automatically think, "I hope she doesn't put her fingers in the fire because it will burn her." Its nature
is to be hot. Okay, next paragraph. These are some other thoughts
on the features.
You should know that my main ideas about characteristics are those three elements, but let's talk about other things together. Let's talk about other features regarding the concept of characteristics. ,RANG BZHIN YOD PA MA YIN NA, ,GZHAN GYI DNGOS PO GA LA YOD, It is very complicated. If you think about it carefully, fire has two natures.
One originates from within, the other from
without. For example, the color of fire. "Originating from the outside world" means "
depending on the external environment".
So which element... the element present in the wood will cause the flame to have a different
color? But it will be hot
. Heat is the characteristic of fire; color is secondary. This is the second characteristic. The second
characteristic of fire is that it can be
created by other forces. The inherent properties of fire should originate from within. So no one can make fire hot, but they can change its color by adding different chemical elements. Everything
about fire is contained in these two things. It's either an inherent characteristic or merely a feature; for example, color depends on other environmental factors.
,GZHAN
GYI DNGOS PO GA LA YOD, There's nothing else about fire. ,GZHAN GYI DNGOS PO'I RANG BZHIN NI, ,GZHAN GYI DNGOS PO YIN ZHES BRJOD,
How can one say that what originates from
elsewhere is one's true nature? When others
believe that nature originates from elsewhere, we say that we are talking about something else that exists independently.
- What's the meaning? Does the color of fire depend on
external factors?
- Yes. However, when this is said, it means that
chemical elements create color. Do
you understand? Is the color of fire part of its innate characteristics? - No
, it changes depending
on the chemical elements. If you
sprinkle chemical elements into a fire, the color will change; the color of the fire originates from external sources
. In other words, as you know, it's secondary. Created by external forces
. But when you hear me say that, you assume it comes from chemical elements, and that's the problem. You even got the minor parts wrong. Forget that the heat of
fire comes from itself; it doesn't
. He is warm, and that warmth comes from you. Forget about that assumed characteristic.
You even misunderstand why the color changed. You thought it was caused by chemical elements. Do you understand?
By the way, that's all related to fire. That's all. That's just how it is, and that's all there is to it.
You know nothing about either of them.
,RANG BZHIN DANG NI GZHAN DNGOS DAG,
,MA GTOGS DNGOS PO GA LA YOD, Fire is its innate characteristic and the combination of its features created by external forces. There was
no other fire besides that. Once these two points are included, it
becomes the essence of fire.
But you don't understand either of them, therefore you don't understand fire
. good. ,RANG BZHIN DANG NI GZHAN DNGOS DAG, ,
YOD NA DNGOS PO 'GRUB PAR 'GYUR, in short. Here he said, "You don't know RANG BZHIN
and
you do
n't know GZHAN DNGOS." You do not understand the basic nature of
fire, its self-generating nature, nor do you understand why it moves, why it has different colors, or why it has different temperatures. You don't understand. ,YOD NA
DNGOS PO 'GRUB PAR 'GYUR,
If the properties and characteristics of fire exist in the way you think they do, then it
is not fire. ,GAL TE DNGOS PO MA GRUB NA,
If there were no
real fire, ,DNGOS MED 'GRUB PAR MI 'GYUR RO, then you would not have the concept of what is called unreal. Without real
fire, it would be difficult to
define what is unreal. If there isn't real cream on the table, then... it's hard for my teacher to say that it's fake cream. Those powders are
fake cream.
If he had never seen real cream, he couldn't... Real cream
defines fake cream, and
fake cream defines real cream
. He didn't just smile and say, "Oh, real cream," if he had never experienced the danger of eating fake cream. [Laughter] I'm always the one who has to
convince the waiter to give him real cream. Good heavens, sometimes it takes half an hour. ,DNGOS PO GZHAN DU GYUR PA NI
, We've discussed this when things become something else. For example, when milk becomes yogurt, ,DNGOS MED YIN PAR SKYE BO SMRA
, SKYE BO SMRA means people say, people in the world say. SKYE BO SMRA means what people in the world would say. What would they say? This is
not how it was originally.
When milk is turned into yogurt, how do people talk about milk? They
said this wasn't how it was supposed to be. It's solid now, but it was originally a liquid. If you can describe something as it was originally, then it has no inherent nature. It's
not what it originally looked like. It is not what it originally was, meaning that whatever changes, if it is not what it was, is
not its characteristic. Milk... When I look at yogurt, I mean milk. It is no longer
milk. When you say it's no longer milk, you're referring to the characteristics of milk. What is being said is that characteristics will end and disappear. It means that it can discard its characteristics. So it doesn't exist inside, right? So it must have originated from somewhere else, right? Then it lacks
inherent characteristics. All it has are features created by external forces, such as the seeds in your mind. Do you understand? good.
Next, this photo shows real cream. I always see my teacher smiling whenever I see real cream. good. Let's look at the next passage. ,GANG DAG RANG BZHIN GZHAN DNGOS DANG, ,DNGOS DANG DNGOS MED NYID LTA BA, ,DE DAG SANGS RGYAS BSTAN PA LA, ,DE
NYID MTHONG BA MA YIN NO, This is typical... GANG DAG RANG BZHIN GZHAN DNGOS
These are
two things:
RANG BZHIN and GZHAN DNGOS. RANG BZHIN means "his characteristics", innate characteristics. GZHAN DNGOS refers to its "additional features" that are added due to the external environment. Is DANG, DNGOS DANG DNGOS MED NYID LTA BA real or fake? Is this real cream or creamer? Is it made from cow's milk and tastes delicious, or is it made from flour? Here he makes
two distinctions: characteristics and other variable features; real milk and fake milk.
Two
sets of differences, two distinct points. The differences between the two groups. "When I describe it to you," Nagarjuna said to another, "you still believe they exist independently." By the way, when I speak of truth or falsehood, I will ask you questions. Is it
true that reality can only be defined by unreality? Is it true that traits, innate traits, can only be defined by changeable characteristics? In Buddhism, you need to
see the short
to understand the tall.
Because many people will tell you that I always see this situation in
some Burmese schools or American schools.
They would say that emptiness is the
result of comparison; nothing in itself is
real
because it must be
compared with other things. Is
this emptiness? Is this a
dependency origin?
No, that's not it. It has absolutely
no relation to that. The
entire explanation of emptiness is ridiculous.
Height is not defined by shortness;
height depends on the seeds of height in your consciousness. It's that
simple.
You can still be tall even if you're
not short, because the seed of height is in your consciousness, even if you're not short. Height does
not
depend on being
short. It depends on what you did to someone yesterday. [Laughter] Do you understand? Things are not derived through comparison. Reality is not defined by human beings. In Buddhism, in true Buddhism, characteristics do not arise from temporary and changeable features. The characteristics depend on your seed. good. If you believe that greatness is determined by comparison
, or that characteristics are only characteristics through comparison of these accidental and changeable features
, then
those who say this—DE DAG
SANGS RGYAS BSTAN PA LA,
,DE NYID MTHONG BA MA YIN—
they didn't see emptiness. Yes, they didn't see emptiness.
DE BZHIN—"Thus
they didn't see…" means "thus."
Here,
if you believe that the nature of things, in a certain respect, can only be obtained
through comparison, then you believe that characteristics come
from themselves, or that characteristics originate from the
comparison.
Then you don't understand the nature of things.
This is a joke. Do you understand?
You do not understand the true nature of things.
DE NYID -- The true nature of things.
This is a joke.
Okay?
Incidentally, as the Buddhist teachings state,
SANGS RGYAS BSTAN PA LA, line three,
you do not understand the Dharma.
Then, I don't know why
I found this picture for everyone:
three people wearing blindfolds.
They are like people who have a
wrong concept of characteristics or self-existence;
they seem to be wandering in darkness.
I just wanted you to see this picture
because I want you to be grateful
for why Nagarjuna Bodhisattva
repeatedly said,
"They did not understand the Buddha's teachings."
Historically, why did he seem
particularly concerned about this? One hundred US dollars!
[Female voice, inaudible]
- Historically, historically [female voice,
inaudible]
Why does he repeatedly return to this topic:
"You did not understand the Buddha's teachings."
- [Venerable Jigme] Perhaps because [inaudible]
- Very well, $50 is available now.
Jigme said that there was another system that contradicted his teachings
- [Jigme] and it was a prevalent system
- which had been prevalent for a long time. Fifty US dollars
- [Jigme Lingpa] Two hundred years
- Seven hundred years
- [Jigme Lingpa] Abhidharma
- Yes, Abhidharma
People have misunderstood for seven hundred years.
They quoted the Buddha. Recite the Buddha's words.
They can memorize them.
They can recite all the scriptures.
And according to Professor Nick's verses, the
Buddha kept it, you know. ． ．
Emptiness is also described in Abhidharma texts.
In his Sixty Points of Perfection, Nagarjuna proved that emptiness is also discussed in the
scriptures of Theravada Buddhism.
He realized this,
so one can imagine how frustrated Nagarjuna must have been.
He resisted seven hundred years of misunderstanding.
He tried to stand alone
before a seven-hundred-year-old wave, saying,
"Hey everyone, this is all wrong!"
[Imitations came wave after wave.]
Therefore, he had to constantly return to the classics and
say, "You don't understand." "You
didn't get it."
That's not what he meant.
Understand?
Can't you hear the seven hundred years of frustration in his voice?
Okay, so
this is what it means to have your eyes covered. It will remind you once again that it is extremely important for
us to now switch to
a key point in Buddhism
. I'm
sorry, this last class today is only
halfway through
because everyone is very tired, but let's continue.
,BCOM LDAN DNGOS DANG DNGOS
MED PA, ,MKHYEN PAS KA TA YA NA YI, ,GDAM NGAG LAS NI YOD PA DANG, ,MED PA GNYIS KA'ANG DGAG PA MDZAD,
Very, very Nagarjuna.
00:27:58,170 --> 00:28:00,080 is
very important.
For the two husbands in the kitchen, it is very important.
BCOM ` DAS – Bhagavan – Buddha said
he understands. MKHYEN PA
Buddha knows the
difference between DNGOS and DNGOS MED.
Here, DNGOS and DNGOS MED
refer to the real
and the unreal. The Buddha understood the difference between the real and the unreal. The
real husband in the kitchen,
and the unreal husband in the kitchen.
He was aware of this difference.
In the *Katyayana Sutra*,
this is one of his beloved disciples.
Katyayana is
very important in the scriptures
related to the Wheel of Life. He personally witnessed the first drawing of the Wheel of Life, and
then returned home to tell the story.
In short, the Buddha gave Katyayana personal advice.
I specifically looked for it
, and you found some, but it wasn't clear enough.
LAS NI YOD PA DANG MED PA
GNYIS KA'ANG DGAG PA MDZAD
The
Buddha denies the possibility of things existing, and at the
same time, the Buddha also denies the possibility of things not existing. The
Buddha
denied the existence of things,
and at the same time denied that things could not exist. Okay? This is something that Nagarjuna Bodhisattva repeatedly emphasized as extremely important. It's especially helpful for understanding the
two husbands in the kitchen. A reward of one hundred dollars.
In the kitchen, where is the existence of things denied,
and where is the non-existence of things denied?
You need to answer both correctly to win the $100 reward. What exists in the kitchen, and what does not? - [Jinmei Venerable] The husband you created. - The husband you created does exist. - [Jinmei Venerable] You did
not create that husband
. - Yes, that husband who
wasn't my fault
doesn't exist. The statement that something does not exist is actually true; this is called the extreme of existence. The non-existence of what is said to truly exist is called the extreme of non-existence. You've gone too far
.
If the husband in the kitchen isn't my fault, then
he doesn't exist. Feel sorry. If it weren't for the
husband in the kitchen's fault, he wouldn't exist at all. Do you understand? [Female voice, unclear]
And because the husband in the kitchen is my fault, he does exist. Therefore, at the same time, this
husband both exists and does
not exist. Denying his existence is a problem. It's wrong to deny the existence of a
husband who is at fault. At the same time, it is also wrong to deny the presence of any husband in the kitchen. Do you understand? Two extremes.
We call it a cliff fall. Actually, this diagram is a
crossing... I was trying to find a bridge in Arizona.
Good luck. This is called the Middle Way. And you
try to traverse between non-
existence and existence
. If you believe that a husband who isn't at fault truly exists, then you've fallen to one side. If you think you
don't have a husband. Then you fall to the other side.
This is the most important source of this concept in all Buddhist scriptures. This is the place. yeah. OK This also means now is a good time to take a Sanskrit lesson.
I did some research and found that one extreme view
is that his existence comes from himself. Another extreme view is that he doesn't exist at all. These have specific terms in Buddhism. It's called YOD PA'IMTHA' and MED PA'I MTHA' YOD MTHA' and MED MTHA'. Repeat after me: YOD MTHA'
[student repeats] MED MTHA' [student repeats] YOD MTHA' [student repeats] MED MTHA' [student repeats] YOD PA'I MTHA' means an extreme statement: His existence is... [student]
coming from his own side, from his own side, not
because I yell at the child. This is called... By the way, I'm really considering my next book... I want to write a book about two husbands, okay? bhūtah (bhutah is
called bhūtah (bhutah). Repeat after me: 'bhutahkoti' bhutahkoti, bhutahkoti.
'
bhutah' means it exists. 'koti' means extreme or cliff. 'koti' means cliff or extreme. 'koti' also has many meanings, but
that's another matter. Okay? So √bhū means to exist, it comes from… In the Indo-European system, it's called √bhū, thus
giving rise to
words like be and build
. What about that Sanskrit lesson? Oh
, sorry. I must have missed it. Oops. Be, build, and physics all come from the root √bheu. Physics is also from the root √bheu. 'koti' I didn't find many, except for cut, which means angle, acute angle. Something
you'll fall from. And koṭika (kotika) is the MU in MU BZHI MU GSUM. $30 bonus MU BZHI MU GSUM?
[Female voice, unclear] MU BZHI MU GSUM, MU BZHI MU GSUM? You know MU BZHI MU GSUM [Female voice, unclear]
- Yes, how so?
Combinations. Four combinations. The previous answer gets $20. It means four... Just like you
're on a four-cornered table.
Four possible combinations. Koti, called 'kotika'. Okay, very good. So what's its opposite?
What's the opposite of Bhutakoti, Christina? Abhūtakoṭi (abhutakoti), abhutakoti. It means the extreme of thought. If it doesn't come from its own side, it does
n't exist in the kitchen.
That's another extreme. Of these two extremes we've
learned, which one is inherent in humans? The answer is classic, you can chew on it, it's the extreme where it
doesn't exist at all. This comes from a very bad explanation of emptiness. But it's also a commonly learned explanation. If he is not who I think he is, then he does not exist at all. People
who usually say this do not understand the true meaning of emptiness. Okay, let's continue. Next sentence. ,
GAL TE RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD NA, ,DE NI MED NYID MI 'GYUR RO, ,RANG BZHIN GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA NI, ,NAM YANG 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO, These are two different concepts. And they are RANG LUGS, our lineage system. GAL TE RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD NA If
the existence of any entity originates from its own nature—
meaning
the characteristic we've been discussing—then MED NYID
MI 'GYUR RO
—it absolutely cannot change.
Okay?
If its characteristic is inherent, it can never
become something else, meaning it can never stop
,
because stopping is also a kind of change.
Therefore, if something has a characteristic from itself—
because this characteristic is eternal—
Things can never stop because
they have a constant property.
This is a very interesting concept.
And he said it's like
NAM MKHA' MI SGRIB PA
- Tim, what is SGRIB PA? Do
you remember SGRIB PA?
SGRIB PA, MA SGRIB means
to cover, to conceal.
Then he said, Guru Chonni said
NAM MKHA' MI SGRIB PA,
what does that mean? What is NAM MKHA'?
[Female voice, unclear]
No, not the sky
- [female] Space
- empty space.
You must say empty space. There are
four kinds of space.
Therefore you must say
empty space. It will never change. So he said, then all things... If things have their properties, because these properties will never change, then things can never change. Because if they change, they will lose their properties. This also means that if properties are permanent, then things are permanent. So it's like empty space is permanent,
whether the earth is in that space,
whether the planet earth is in that space,
or whether you destroy the earth, that
space will always be there.
MA SGRIB is open.
And it won't get blocked.
It's not like a box. It's like space.
,RANG BZHIN GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA NI,
,NAM YANG 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
Therefore, if the nature of something never changes,
that thing will last forever. If the
nature of something changes,
then it's not a nature, is it?
If fire cools down,
then what's the use of having a nature?
Understand?
Then another person came.
My goodness,
he mentioned us first, then another person,
and he didn't say he was exchanging.
Okay, next.
,RANG BZHIN YOD PA MA YIN NA,
,GZHAN DU 'GYUR PA GANG GI YIN,
If the nature of milk could never change,
then where does yogurt come from?
then who turned it into milk?
Sorry, who turned it into yogurt?
If the milk's nature
could never change,
then who turned into Yogurt?
Who turned it into yogurt?
Then we say,
if milk does have an inherent nature, then what changes?
Okay?
This is called RIGS PA MGO MTSHUNGS
RIGS PA MGO MTSHUNGS,
which means parallel reasoning. Let
me say it again.
He said…
Sorry, let me see.
If things don't have an inherent nature, how
can you say
it becomes something else? If
milk doesn't have an inherent nature, how can you
say milk becomes yogurt?
If milk doesn't have a certain property, how can you
say
it transforms into something else?
If you didn't have a driver's license to begin with,
how can you say
my driver's license is fake?
How about this example? [Laughs]
That's someone else.
Then we say, "No, you don't understand.
If it does have a property, then it can't change." If
it doesn't have a property,
don't tell me it can't change.
That's his argument.
If it's not something, how can it change?
And we'll say, "No, you don't understand.
If it is something, how can it change?"
[Laughs]
Understand? Interesting, right? Confused?
Halfway through the second half, it's our turn.
Thank you, Nagarjuna.
Okay.
Then, I don't know.
I forgot why I put up a picture of a sculptor. Right,
the concept is, can you change
something that can't be changed, something like that.
Okay, let's continue
. Don't worry, we're almost at the end. The
next line is even more famous than the previous ones.
I said this very famous,
very famous verse.
,YOD CES BYA BA RTAG PAR 'DZIN, Repeat
after me YOD CES BYA BA [Student repeats]
RTAG PAR 'DZIN [Student repeats]
MED CES BYA BA [Student repeats]
CHAD PAR LTA [Student repeats] DE PHYIR [Student repeats]
YOD DANG MED PA LA [Student repeats]
MKHAS PAS GNAS PAR [Student repeats]
MI BYA'O [Student repeats]
If you believe that things exist,
then you fall into the trap that things can never be changed. The
extreme idea:
If you think things don't exist,
then you fall into the extreme idea that things never came to be.
Therefore, you great ones
should stay in the middle.
Hence, there is Madhyamika.
What is another name for wisdom?
Yes, Madhyamika.
Madhyamika.
This is another name for Prajna.
Where have you seen this other name?
One hundred dollars bounty
[Christina] Lama Chuni's... title
[weak voice]
Almost there
- [Tim] Madhyamaka
- Yes, Tim got one hundred dollars.
One hundred dollars for Tim. Okay,
Chandrakirti didn't
title his book Madhyamika.
He called it Madhyamaka.
This one related to Madhyamika is called Madhyamaka. A
commentary on Madhyamika.
Okay.
Here,
if you think things exist,
then they can never change.
If you think things don't exist,
then you are a nihilist.
Okay?
Therefore, a true wise person
should stay between the two views.
You should be between the two views.
What does this mean in the context of the kitchen? Three hundred dollars!
[Pau] I understand...
- Slow down, slow down.
That's a lot of money. [
Laughter] What is the
middle ground in the kitchen?
- [Pau] When you realize your
husband is yelling at you
because you yelled at the kids last week
.
- Good.
So that exists.
Now, what doesn't exist in the kitchen?
- [Pau] The "I didn't do anything"
husband.
- That "I didn't do anything"
husband doesn't exist, yes.
So stay in the middle.
Understand?
Three hundred dollars.
[Exhale]
Pudge, she'll treat you to a big meal.
Okay?
[Someone's voice, unclear]
Good.
,GANG ZHIG RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD PA, ,DE NI MED PA
MIN PAS RTAG, ,SNGON BYUNG
DA LTAR MED CES PA,
,DES NA CHAD PAR THAL BAR 'GYUR.
Okay. Then he extended the meaning of immutability
and never beginning.
Incidentally, these two extremes,
immutability and cessation, This refers to the result of a specific argument. They
are described as the result of a
specific argument. If the husband comes from his own side, he will never change -- RTAG PA. So what about the other one? CHAD PA. I think
if he comes from, and if he doesn't come from his
own side,
he doesn't exist. Then he must stop. Understand? Okay. And then I have a picture I made especially for you. The Middle Way about two husbands, okay
? If you
think he only comes from his own side, you fall to the right side of the bridge. If you think that
if he doesn't come from his own side,
he can't exist,
then
you fall to the left side of the bridge. If
you stop at the Middle Way, you
have a happy relationship.
Yeah! Oh, sorry, this is the last picture for this lesson. So let's wrap this
up. What
is
the name of this chapter? We explored characteristics. Do things have inherent existence? The conclusion is that things
do not have inherent existence. Because even if things have characteristics, like the heat of fire, seemingly in the fire, it
also comes from us.
That's the bottom line. So things have no inherent existence. Okay. What does that mean in
relation to the Medicine Buddha mantra? [Woman's voice, unclear] Yes, what happens if you chant the Medicine Buddha mantra with bad intentions? The characteristics of this mantra will manifest. Are there any beneficial characteristics? No. If
you
chant these mantras with a competitive mindset, then these mantras will harm people, okay? Cool, right? That's the
emptiness of these mantras
. They are
without inherent existence. Cool.
See you next time! Yay!